<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: AWS | Balaji Vajjala's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/categories/aws/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-16T13:02:09-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Balaji Vajjala]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 4]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-4/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T11:23:17-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-4</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Choosing an instance type: Part 4</h3>

<p>As mentioned in <a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-1/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 1">part 1 of this
series</a> (Creating
a LAMP Stack AMI), a common concern among most customers is to choose
the right instance type.</p>

<p>It is important to do the capacity planning. Before you choose instance
type ask yourself the following three questions:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Is the application Memory intensive CPU intensive or Network
intensive? For this question to be meaningful put a monitoring
system in place and collect the data for a few weeks of real usage.</p></li>
<li><p>What is the expected request count at peak hours?</p></li>
<li><p>What is the minimum number of instances you want to run in
non-business hours?</p></li>
</ol>


<p><a href="https://docs.google.com/a/flux7.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AkmUqlScRGp8dGJTNndjY0VjTURid3FTV2dNMEljOUE#gid=0">https://docs.google.com/a/flux7.com/spreadsheet/ccc?key=0AkmUqlScRGp8dGJTNndjY0VjTURid3FTV2dNMEljOUE#gid=0</a></p>

<p>Make sure to run at least 2 servers for high availability.  During times
of fewer loads, choose two m1.small instances for non-business hours
like weekends. This would optimize cost instead of using 2 large
instances for the same request.</p>

<p>Different instance types have different capacity levels. If the
application is memory intensive choose and use m1. class. If the
application is CPU intensive then choose and use c1. class.</p>

<p>Network bandwidth varies between different instance types. If the
application requires more bandwidth (ex: video streaming applications)
choose higher instance types irrespective of Memory or CPU to get better
bandwidth.</p>

<p>To know more about each instance types visit the following link.</p>

<p><a href="http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/instance-types/">http://aws.amazon.com/ec2/instance-types/</a></p>

<p>Start with micro/small instance for any workload. Do the Load run
starting with the minimum number of users and increase the load
gradually. Also scale the servers vertically or horizontally gradually
until it reaches the maximum capacity. This would give a clearer picture
of the number of instances required to serve the maximum or minimum
load. Closely watch the CloudWatch graphs to understand usage statistics
better.</p>

<p>An interesting question at this juncture could be as follows: Can 4
m1.medium instances be preferred to 2 large instances? Yes of course.
However, network bandwidth varies from one instance type to other. Given
that, it is wise to choose 2 large instances instead of 4 m1.medium
instances as it is easier to handle lesser number of instances.</p>

<p>(Note: DB server health needs to be checked when a load test is run.
Increasing the app servers count may not improve the performance all the
time. If DB queries are the bottleneck, chances are high for a bad
performance. Consider scaling up the DB server capacity as well.)</p>

<p>Based on the instance type identified from the load run, tune the PHP
memory settings and Apache prefork MPM client connections.</p>

<p>Check out the following links to know more about fine tuning Apache and
PHP</p>

<p><a href="http://www.hosting.com/support/linux/tuning-the-apache-prefork-mpm/">http://www.hosting.com/support/linux/tuning-the-apache-prefork-mpm/</a></p>

<p><a href="http://icreatestuff.co.uk/blog/article/apache-performance-tuning">http://icreatestuff.co.uk/blog/article/apache-performance-tuning</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T11:23:14-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Load Test the Environment: Part 3</h3>

<p>In part 3 of the Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS series,</p>

<p>After setting up your application autoscaling, it’s important to load
run the application in order to understand the minimum and maximum
number of instances required for each application.</p>

<p><a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-setting-up-austoscaling-groups-part-2/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Setting Up Austoscaling Groups : Part 2">Read Part 2 to learn more about setting up autoscaling
groups.</a></p>

<p>First, fire the load run. For this article we’ve used HP LoadRunner
because it provides more detailed results than others, but there are
also other load runner tools to choose from. Be sure to run the load
from multiple IP addresses or else the ELB may not distribute it equally
across all instances. HP LoadRunner helps you use multiple nodes in
order to generate the load.</p>

<p>Update the Auto Scaling Group’s minimum and maximum instance counts.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/nXhTs4kEqjzxfAy8aGdgqLvC_yKninSiyM3pClGWhemLXPWFjr_6Y5NU8xnf2j7twuJgVx2TO4tvs8fjm2K1c8y6C23NN8lacgef-JEH4621AXZITbYAAKRF4w" alt="" /></p>

<p>For the this article, we’ve set the minimum and maximum instance counts
at 2 and 8 respectively.</p>

<p>Now change your Auto Scaling Policies. A scaling policy specifies
whether to scale the auto scaling group up or down, and by how much.
Here we’ve chosen 2 instances for Scale Up and Scale Down policies.
These policies automatically increase or decrease the instances
according to your defined conditions in order to maintain performance
and minimize cost.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/3G9JdQa1GNjF_2fWOrZ10y-cpc3m8_6gtTH2Y046OK3LoiaMYGx0Nm_N4LsBcBhhRhA3cxr7D1sMlCv90ewW9rZ8QCr8amOHqivVcZZmML7Bx-XMIeM7wdN1Nw" alt="" /></p>

<p>Next, <strong>increase the load</strong> gradually with LoadRunner. Once the CPU
reaches 75% of the instances, Autoscaling will trigger the scale up
policy to launch 2 more instances.</p>

<p>Now <strong>decrease the load</strong> gradually and the CPU instances load should
come down to less than 45%. Autoscaling will then trigger the scale down
policy and delete the additional instances that were launched.</p>

<p>Consider a scenario in which a 2,000-concurrent-request count is reached
during peak hours and 500 users are reached during non-peak hours. For
best load run results, try the following.</p>

<p>Capture load test results and CloudWatch metrics for each of the
following scenarios:</p>

<p>​1. Start the load test with 500 users. Set the minimum instance count
to 2 if you choose large or medium types, and set the maximum instance
count to 4.</p>

<p>​2. Increase the load to 1,000 users. Set the minimum and maximum
instance counts to 2 and 6 respectively.</p>

<p>​3. Increase the load to 2,000 users. Set the minimum and maximum
instance counts to 4 and 10 respectively.</p>

<p>​4. Increase the load to 3,000 users. Set the minimum and maximum
instance counts to 6 and 12 respectively.</p>

<p>Analyze the results for each scenario and note which gives better
throughput and response times. Also check the DB metrics.</p>

<p>Now it will be easy to choose the best instance type and max/min
instance counts..</p>

<p><strong>Shutdown Autoscaling</strong></p>

<p>Update the autoscale group to resize the instance count to 0. This will
terminate all instances launched within the lamp-asg autoscale group.</p>

<p><em>Watch out for the final part of this series tomorrow on how to choose
an instance type. </em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-2/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T11:23:10-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Setting Up Austoscaling Groups : Part 2</h3>

<p>In part 2 of the Autoscaling LAMP in AWS series, let’s discuss how to
create autoscaling launch configuration, autoscaling groups and how to
verify the setup autoscaling.</p>

<h2><strong>Autoscale Implementation</strong> </h2>

<p>Autoscale configuration is now available in console. AWS command lines
are no longer needed for implementation.</p>

<p>Complete the following steps as detailed in <a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-1/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 1">Part
1</a>of
this series in order to set up autoscaling :</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Configure AMI to launch the Instances.</p></li>
<li><p>Configure Instance type to launch the instances. (Example:
m1.small,m1.large).</p></li>
<li><p>Configure KeyPair Name to access the machines.</p></li>
<li><p>Configure Security Group to allow the Instances to communicate with
other components.</p></li>
<li><p>Keep the ELB name readily available.</p></li>
<li><p>Keep your availability zones ready. (Example: us-east-1a,
us-east-1b).</p></li>
<li><p>Set the minimum number of instances for Maximum and Desired
Capacity. (Start with zero).</p></li>
<li><p>Set Health Check Type. (ELB).</p></li>
<li><p>Set Region.</p></li>
<li><p>Change Capacity Cooldown time.</p></li>
<li><p>Adjust for scale up and scale down.</p></li>
</ul>


<h2><strong>1. Create the Autoscaling Launch Config</strong> </h2>

<p>Log in to the AWS console and navigate to Services-> EC2-> Launch
Configuration.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-E7LhgP_GnMeKXQHtHPieeiqZBbrD3TauY5FHvA90y2hvnWMoncO5gEJASGmYd_v1HjDIzIr949-gjX7N2DlCtzCyO5iwZnUd481qEyiHKVkxhH40xDL3xiTzQ" alt="" /></p>

<p>Click on “Create Autoscaling Group”.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/8MJM4YJXpOnamUnIZdfPkHZDJJ_iyVXg1qj373NTmPKZbihu4C2nqYcm2zvCacxycBN1OjzxbpANVSI7W4t7a8LYo15FbooKxx0UlXXkpJwuWxSNX7ZfSYm-PA" alt="" /></p>

<p>On the next screen, click on “Create Launch Configuration”.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/8h6Tn5ncvwmpG6qqI5vqulA_qoG6ijs4wtOOWA6nDwuCUCF1_OpD1VSWhlJDimgNNyhp_dmEsVx4DNJkls043s_CbBJ3HK0VUsSUphYjNeM3Qnlx1clgXZ5jAA" alt="" /></p>

<p>Create a new launch configuration. The name of the launch configuration
must be unique within the scope of the client’s AWS account.</p>

<p><strong>Choose AMI:</strong> Go to My AMIs and select the LAMP AMI created.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/SJXQcn4aWSm83eKHuKKZHJomaUvLwJShg8w5M1Q6wEXXNiUv61JNoiaKMYlaacP4TYT8kTvJju2vDKK23RReWFLgLxRGb68xaSuMbHzjQ0H74evkNtINH_T_xQ" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Choose Instance Type:</strong> We’ve selected a micro instance for our
example.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/e7lh5P4VR8i9qJ5QgxUK1PBN6in9HQNpU0cjznY6Giemq8RZrF2wBEfmlL_cCS_cDUBKKUHkmU__YC6YPiNncXXhbXMq9BRE3tLSbDewJR8MZ8upoWi0OwIp2w" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Configure Details:</strong> Give a name for the Launch Configuration\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/kP646CGpnJLDO-44macZIU6A4FMSeLpu8kSq6hpFIstb_heGHWMCRwtn5EpOw8YZdvCANbd-5Pur5SNw_OaWg7432_WdQ1Rbi9QUsR6FMUIo71Y6REwKA5wJ2w" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Add Storage:</strong> Keep the values on default.</p>

<p><strong>Configure the Security Group:</strong>Select the Security group to launch the
autoscaling instances. Review the details and create the Launch
Configuration.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/rd0tjYvJyMzG0irkmsj9LZSXrxigf93tfOhOLUtcrQ-c1Pk2XXsOF7ksRbu4BY_6PvPfMWqC9bF4NZcy1aNLBOfUd91vjV9shjfA9IRAA5MNSJXb6sPuVa8gHA" alt="" /></p>

<p>In the next window, select “KeyPair” to access the instances.</p>

<h2><strong>2. Create the Auto Scaling Group</strong> </h2>

<p>Create a new Auto Scaling group with a specified name and other
attributes. When you make the creation request, the Auto Scaling group
is ready for use in other calls.</p>

<p>Navigate to EC2-> Auto Scaling Groups-> Create Autoscaling Group.</p>

<p>Select the existing Launch Configuration (lamp-launch-1) and go to “Next
Step”.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/N9-2P0wrXtd1IKWO58H1i7s6MRx0w_toDG5wjmtvsw0v5wUamXz6oIC88g-YYqnP5H9OTobjDc_X9Hf1shLrn_5tTO4HLuHHUomu8qE8OYv3oLEDp02urv0U4g" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Configure Autoscaling Group Details:</strong></p>

<p>Give a name to the Auto Scaling Group.</p>

<p>Group Size: Start with zero instances in order to avoid the immediate
creation of instances. The exact number of required instances can be set
after these steps are completed, but just set cost optimization values
to 0 for now.</p>

<p><strong>Availability Zones:</strong></p>

<p>Choose 2 availability zones in order to maintain high availability.</p>

<p>In “Advanced Details” choose the values as shown below.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/YL14QA7srKzFlnQLXuXtIxo0wrB51aDQuOj8fR5YXDYErg2usKCEaKJ57fKN6UahjFP0KFOTkr_y8odlPVWqDh2z3OMwy_iUCRJ5ubiQ4EsOTTNSLKbz8IU2UQ" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Configure Scaling Policies:</strong> Keep minimum and maximum instances count
to zero.</p>

<p><strong>Increase Group Size:</strong> Keep the name at default.</p>

<p><strong>Execute Policy:</strong> Click on “Add new alarm”.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/ysaxf1OR2wazrUt1lvdkYI-YRoVdijKoJD4m6DDlGOHld-LO_mtz24-kOmvyTHybJPIEK_VOKV_UC5ybIwwt9jKtJhZ_3N3J1B_4e5P1iAyIsynEpODx6S4gKQ" alt="" /></p>

<p>A popup window will appear for creating a “Cloud Watch Alarm”.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/eqvhUKlpyNKv7vWQiAI95g5oUQxp9KpqQJ0WCEJjFNfCfn-PIBtaYEPf7k8T2BrlCxN8EoF6utdR5c67tMMk-K0CW-upVZIKR1jOTumOoiwic5fEvZndn8_aEA" alt="" /></p>

<p>For this example, we chose CPU Load average as the autoscaling trigger.
Whenever the average CPU load of app servers goes beyond 75% for 5
minutes, autoscaling will trigger the auto-scale-up-policy to launch the
1 instance and attach to load balancer. The application here is CPU
intensive and requires more computing power, so we chose the CPU Load
Average as the autoscale triggering event.</p>

<p>You can choose any Cloudwatch metric to trigger the autoscaling policy.
For example, Disk read/writes, Network In/Out, ELB request count, ELB
latency, etc.</p>

<p><strong>Decrease Group size:</strong>\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/wxwMuiWm-72K4zGTx-oT56LdXvjhQXNQZPLg_HXPMb89ey5CEtmOV76euYKqLwbYKm88kOAlmSrW6xfRImjIefcQ7LVFOcUIRoyZ5t3xF_JffVy7R96Ypk8lMg" alt="" /></p>

<p><strong>Configure Notifications:</strong> If you’ve already created notifications,
select one to receive the notifications of Autoscaling events, else skip
this step for now.</p>

<p>Review the details and click on “Create Autoscaling Group”.</p>

<p>Auto Scaling evaluates the health of each Amazon EC2 instance in the
Auto Scaling Group and automatically replaces unhealthy instances in
order to keep the Auto Scaling Group size fixed. That ensures that the
application is getting the expected compute capacity.</p>

<p>In this example, we’ve chosen to scale down the environment when the
average CPU load lowers to 40% for 5 minutes.</p>

<h2><strong>Verify Autoscaling</strong> </h2>

<p>After completing the previous steps, it’s time to test autoscaling.</p>

<p>​1. Update the Autoscaling group minimum and maximum instances count to
2 and 4. You can change these later to fit your specific requirements.</p>

<p>Navigate to EC2-> Auto Scaling Group- > lamp-asg-1.</p>

<p>Right click on “lamp-asg-1” and select “Edit”.</p>

<p>In the “Details” tab, update Desired Min and Max values to 1, and then
save.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/hxxgnuVeJGgoMHPJvsr5oTeghIkuhJv4_hX0U1YtdjpO57N84IN4KmuSk4cO9cYeTH7JiSD9EMVAXCwS8z5v0-lZ3Gf4jW67oGNflBhgr10tiUVHbn9lpjE8oQ" alt="" /></p>

<p>Now, navigate to Services->EC2->Instances.</p>

<p>You can see that a new instance has been launched and attached to ELB.\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/GPJHyEzUrO4LtbxCSzT6rHiz_RLPIIkmeIS--__XDuzFiW2dLSZwZhSwkvHG2KvW5CJ6Kx8DpvjEXo8Xgbw7Q8HBa6cfNUu2Mf6XAM6jpx-8LVKxEUMNeXCVHA" alt="" /></p>

<p>\</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/9_cNWARusMs6T9rypbPZWakid_pmJpMwBWLXuPhwaRlpiXLU5XFjQDGzBAYbPTtjSiupY8tELI5s8ROwgZtKCvfKhxVsagLXYoKCl_MnWqvnqrOGAoqj-wHGOg" alt="" /></p>

<p>If your health check is configured properly, the instance status will
turn into “In Service” rather quickly. Always have a minimum of 2
instances running in order to maintain high availability.</p>

<p>​2. How to Update Launch Configuration: It’s not possible to update the
existing Launch configuration, so you’ll have to create a new Launch
configuration and edit the Autoscaling Group to use that new
configuration.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/_bDZv08DtcohHQkG5s0e2_0rd3VnkzImL-87T5wfku5cmvL69tgMhMwKc71Vo-zgVbVImT-HaD0f_fo7dcv5F0JmkbXZGpllnhldKILcPVdgYR7nKZ0qaRniwQ" alt="" /></p>

<p>Now, start the application load run and find out the minimum and maximum
instances required for your application to handle the load. Then update
the AutoScaling Group to meet your needs.</p>

<p>Watch out for  Part 3 of this series to understand <a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-load-test-the-environment-part-3/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Load Test the Environment: Part 3">how to load run an
application</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS : Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-1/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T11:23:04-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-creating-a-lamp-stack-ami-part-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 1</h3>

<p>This is part 1 of the Autoscaling for LAMP in AWS series. The
step-by-step guide would walk you through</p>

<p><a href="index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS |Creating a LAMP Stack AMI : Part 1">Part 1: Creating a LAMP Stack
AMI</a></p>

<p><a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-setting-up-austoscaling-groups-part-2/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Setting Up Austoscaling Groups : Part 2">Part 2: Setting up Autoscaling
Groups. </a></p>

<p><a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-load-test-the-environment-part-3/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Load Test the Environment: Part 3">Part 3: Load Test the
environment</a></p>

<p><a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-choosing-an-instance-type-part-4/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Choosing an instance type: Part 4">Part 4: Choose instance
type</a></p>

<p>First, let’s discuss how to prepare the AMI, create an ELB and RDS,
verify the application and terminate the instance.</p>

<h2><strong>Prepare AMI</strong> </h2>

<p>In Autoscaling, create an AMI with all required packages installed. This
AMI will be used as a template to launch instances in autoscaling. For
LAMP Stack, you should install and fine tune the latest versions of
Apache and PHP.</p>

<p>​1. Log in to AWS console.</p>

<p>​2. Navigate to EC2 services. Make sure to switch to the desired region
before launching instances.</p>

<p>​3. Click on “Launch instance”.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/hRoQeC1-aimLHiAt0ptacAxdMqlX8w0N19bEmMo8vm31e0n3-PRzWJLd6gg5TUn2FgokMj6n9y72S6gE_XKS0jNx9tHGv5kqD9TKz5qM0vYhu9TIF5FBAG6C-Q" alt="" /></p>

<p>​4. Select your favorite <strong>Linux AMI</strong> in Classic Wizard.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh6.googleusercontent.com/aWfL4g9PfAqaFTg3uI0Ntv52hSxUyPCNKN5Sf8Y4R5zYyjGOmHeA2zi6pGk59F9NiNJa16n27rSk111xlUJUt24oCLPdQfBZMr0k5yhCZpQ6B_ibxzU9hQRKeA" alt="" /></p>

<p>For this article we used CentOS 6.3 from the community AMIs, but
OpenSuse and Ubuntu are also good choices.</p>

<p>​5. Launch a <strong>micro</strong> instance from the selected AMI with the desired
<strong>Security group</strong> and <strong>Key pair</strong>. Remember, this instance is only for
creating an AMI and will be terminated once <strong>LAMP Stack</strong> is installed
on it.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/_U5YNCpt3CelshRRvlBG8CLKp8tYd64u1lwFWqqZcN48v3UjL9GBOfHoxL3EXJ9pXOk3tNz0Ig049xbwJa4gIsNvr4Z869PFqwkSfBDkJ8GK1PU9olC7ktBn7w" alt="" /></p>

<p>​6. Now log in to the instance and perform the <strong>PHP</strong> and Apache
installation steps. For this article, we used <strong>Cygwin</strong> to connect the
<strong>Linux</strong> servers. Make sure you open port 22 to allow <strong>SSH</strong> access
using security groups.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/Al62wHOtPAxqNRUh_kr47FmQqMSycjLKMJ9zSz47OfIWUVDENcSi6ypdoBaiABQ9Rlr33kid0Be8a-1KuyLDYhFbea4Fw4rdJKxGSoDfbQZP6iClUbDTnUmFGA" alt="" /></p>

<p>We modified the “default” security group to open the SSH port. We
recommend that you not completely open port 22 for SSH, but rather allow
incoming requests to SSH from your specific IP address. In our case the
IP address was 49.206.166.12.</p>

<p><code>
$ ssh –I LAMP_AMI.pem root@ec2-54-254-37-17.ap-southeast-1.compute.amazonaws.commailto:root@ec2-54-254-37-17.ap-southeast-1.compute.amazonaws.com
mailto:root@ec2-54-254-37-17.ap-southeast-1.compute.amazonaws.com
$ yum install httpd.x86_64 httpd-devel.x86_64 mod_ssl.x86_64 php.x86_64 php-common.x86_64 php-devel.x86_64 php-gd.x86_64 php-mbstring.x86_64 php-mysql.x86_64 php-pdo.x86_64 php-soap.x86_64 php-xml.x86_64 php-xmlrpc.x86_64 php-pecl-apc-devel.x86_64 php-pecl-memcache.x86_64 -y
</code></p>

<p>Once you’ve successfully executed these commands, Apache and PHP will
install. Note that the commands we’ve used are specific to CentOS 6.3.
Choosing a different OS or a different CentOS may cause these commands
to fail to execute. T<strong>he php modules listed above are required for
WordPress setup and they may vary depending upon your requirements.</strong></p>

<p>Now update the PHP and Apache configurations for your Instance types and
for the expected load on application. We used t1.Micro for this article.
Keep in mind that a production system’s instance types need to be chosen
very carefully, and that the software must be tuned to those particular
types.</p>

<p><strong><em>Read more on selecting instance types in <a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-choosing-an-instance-type-part-4/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Choosing an instance type: Part 4">Part 4 of this
series.</a></em></strong></p>

<p>Install Postfix to send email notification for the script used in the
next step.</p>

<p><code>
$ yum install postfix  
$ chkconfig –level 2345 postfix on
$ chkconfig –level 2345 httpd off
</code></p>

<p>​7. Now all of the required packages are installed and fine-tuned.</p>

<p>So, how does one deploy the code into AMI?</p>

<p>The method described here automates the deployment. One cron job will be
included in AMI, and it will download and deploy the latest available S3
code. That means that code updates will deploy to S3 every time, but not
to instances. Every time a new instance is up, the instance will
automatically download updates from the S3 bucket and deploy them.</p>

<p>What follows is a script scheduled for machine boot-up. It requires
updating based on specific user configurations and file paths.</p>

<p>```</p>

<h1>!/bin/bash</h1>

<p>S3_URL= “<a href="http://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/lamp-deploy/wordpress.zip%E2%80%9D">http://s3-ap-southeast-1.amazonaws.com/lamp-deploy/wordpress.zip%E2%80%9D</a> #Change the following paths as per your requirement.
DOCUMENT_ROOT=</var/www/html>
TEMP_LOC=</tmp>
APACHE_RESTART=<code>/etc/init.d/httpd restart</code></p>

<h1>Get the instance ID from AWS metadata.</h1>

<p>INSTANCE_ID=<code>curl http://169.254.169.254/latest/meta-data/instance-id</code></p>

<h3>download the latest code from s3 and deploy</h3>

<p>cd /tmp
wget $S3_URL
if [ $? –ne 0 ]
then
pkill -9 httpd
mail –s “Code Download Failed from S3##$INSTANCE_ID”  <a href="&#109;&#97;&#x69;&#108;&#x74;&#x6f;&#x3a;&#x74;&#x65;&#115;&#x74;&#x40;&#116;&#101;&#115;&#x74;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;">&#116;&#x65;&#115;&#116;&#64;&#x74;&#x65;&#x73;&#x74;&#x2e;&#x63;&#x6f;&#x6d;</a> #Provide valid email ID here”
exit 1
fi
unzip wordpress.zip
rm –rf  &lt;/var/www/html/<em>>
cp –r wordpress/</em> $DOCUMENT_ROOT
chmod 775 –R $DOCUMENT_ROOT
chown –R apache.root $DOCUMENT_ROOT
$APACHE_RESTART
if [ $? –ne 0 ]
then
pkill -9 httpd
mail –s “Apache startup Failed- $INSTANCE_ID”  <a href="&#109;&#97;&#105;&#x6c;&#x74;&#111;&#x3a;&#x74;&#x65;&#115;&#116;&#x40;&#116;&#x65;&#115;&#116;&#46;&#99;&#111;&#109;">&#116;&#101;&#115;&#x74;&#x40;&#116;&#101;&#x73;&#x74;&#x2e;&#99;&#111;&#x6d;</a> #Provide valid email ID here”
exit 1
fi</p>

<h2>script ends here</h2>

<p>```</p>

<p>Put this bash script into a file in /opt/ directory:</p>

<p><code>
$vim /opt/auto-deploy.sh
$chmod +x /opt/auto-deploy.sh
</code></p>

<p>Open the Crontab and add this script to start at machine boot up:</p>

<p><code>
$ crontab –e
</code></p>

<p>Add the following script:</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/ZiqV0hI1ocrhmDqqLubt01OQdBcmJZqWhNciW6sbPfEz2Iwr99cxoNK4U5actZ6Vqdqat8asF-IwxjJQrVKiutlBZq6A74t9sp1wA0ezqCDbSR09YOjTQrJblX_8VShJfMA" alt="" /></p>

<p>Save your changes and deploy the code by running the script to test
whether or not the application is working as expected. This step is
mandatory before creating an AMI. If you find any issues with the code
or PHP/Apache settings, be sure to fix them before creating an AMI.</p>

<p>Bundle and Upload the Code to S3</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Update the code with RDS DB configuration parameters.</p></li>
<li><p>Now zip the working copy of the code and upload it to the S3
location. The S3 location should match the location in the script,
and also match the zip file name.</p></li>
<li><p>Upload the zip file to the S3 bucket that matches the script. You
can upload the zip file by using the console or any third party tool
like Cloudberry.</p></li>
<li><p>Grant read permissions to download the code from S3 to app servers.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2><strong>Create the ELB</strong> </h2>

<p>Go to Services-> EC2 &ndash;> Load Balancers and select “<strong>Create Load
Balancer</strong>”.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/w-ZRahemXgWVTJcIwpwJYfdXgp7kcmUs23IYzjgdEpwUuYiCkoLJg2dnLs0-5fe8U0UFG1_3qyaNggPesGGHGUq1PwQH5MMo-QowBXfuhGSNthk65DDg5Oc1OA" alt="" /></p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/JU0AmjRaIgFbWa8mdGz2qTlbYTU7wKWiOa93uUVuu-RDO5PPfEVhV1ggUBZ95rr5_z637SffLdwYgHb5srqZlj9GfcL-or3aG3xWsqb9Sd4kJ24LKZ8_84d_YA" alt="" /></p>

<p>Keep Healthy/Unhealthy threshold limits to 4 because that’s proven to be
an ideal value. Also make sure index.html is available in the Document
root. ELB looks for the index.html as a health check and removes the
instance from the load balancer if it doesn’t get the 200 response.
Create the required security groups and key pair for the autoscaling
instances.</p>

<h2><strong>Create RDS</strong> </h2>

<p>​1. Go to Services &ndash;> RDS and select the <strong>MySQL</strong> engine.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/dgMcoX4gkePTWwEYT8soz9RdvW3iMPmmlVlnkgczHmwIDpfmh39BhRUmWRBEdbR0f6FMJi3LtaSW6z_sRhBmk_WYLfls0bv8VQ8r9PFPl52WOX0B12-vCLKBEQ" alt="" /></p>

<p>​2. Select instance types, provide the details for all required fields
and launch the instance. The RDS configuration details chosen for this
article can be seen below.</p>

<p>How should you select the DB instance type? There are many monitoring
tools available for monitoring MySQL performance. If AWS RDS is used for
MySQL, then it’s important to consider CloudWatch metrics. Since it’s
not possible to install agents in RDS, you can rely upon CloudWatch
metrics.</p>

<p>By default, CloudWatch contains all required RDS monitoring metrics. Be
sure to monitor the memory, CPU, DB connections and network I/O before
you scale up the server.</p>

<p>Ideally, m1.small RDS can handle up to 75 concurrent connections easily.
but that depends upon the DB queries and the code.</p>

<p>​3. After launching RDS, open the 3306 port to the app servers group.</p>

<p>​4. Import the DB and try connecting to the application. Then use
standard MySQL commands to import the dump.</p>

<p><strong>Example:</strong> mysql –h rds-endpoint –u user –ppasswwd databasename &lt;
dump.sql</p>

<h2><strong>Verify the Application</strong> </h2>

<p>At this point, it’s mandatory that you thoroughly verify the
application. Make sure to check Login/logout, upload/download and any
other relevant verifications. Create an AMI only after making sure that
the application is working as expected. Fix any issues before proceeding
to the next step.</p>

<h3><strong>Create an AMI</strong></h3>

<p>​1. Delete the command history:</p>

<p><code>
$ history -c
</code></p>

<p>Delete the deployed code and logs files and make things as clean as
possible.</p>

<p>​2. Create an AMI using the micro instance that you’ve configured.</p>

<p>Go to AWS Console->Services->EC2, right click on the instance, and
select “Create Image” (EBS AMI).</p>

<p><img src="https://lh4.googleusercontent.com/pR5iFmQYgO6FygwUB1SNh52dtHhrTr4TDk_G9fd6wlh1ds3V5gnbvhqYdn4yPOPRuQ7JZXwO54xuguOEoczq9yhVx1gsuHuZbVmCRgVFbida6ciJxv0EhNhwdQ" alt="" /></p>

<p>Name the AMI using a date as the naming convention. <strong>Do not</strong> select
“<strong>No reboot</strong>”. Instead, allow it to reboot while creating the AMI. The
reboot will give you a consistent snapshot of EBS.</p>

<p><img src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/5vWSfAF_enz-JCR8PlW-hDts2pvtUSI8yRFYkx8H27K0UdRCntJjTgcHGODGJpiGkXfFpe-XGva-EZUFF5gEDRcPcw5o8xc_8n1ueqYQaK8hpY9WolFLUdrHRw" alt="" /></p>

<p>In a few minutes an AMI will be created and made available.</p>

<p>Keep the root partition as minimal as possible because that helps to
prevent bugs. You don’t need large space for root partition in autoscale
because these instances keep rotating.</p>

<h2><strong>Terminate the Instance</strong> </h2>

<p>Finally, terminate the instance by right clicking on the instance and
selecting “Terminate”. Keep the ELB and RDS running.</p>

<p><strong><em>Watch out for Part 2, same time tomorrow, on how to setup autoscaling
groups!</em></strong></p>

<p><strong>Update</strong>: Check part 2 on how to setup autoscaling groups
<a href="../autoscaling-for-lamp-on-aws-setting-up-austoscaling-groups-part-2/index.html" title="Autoscaling for LAMP on AWS | Setting Up Austoscaling Groups : Part 2">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Deep Dive into AWS Reserved Instances]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/a-deep-dive-into-aws-reserved-instances/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T09:35:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/a-deep-dive-into-aws-reserved-instances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>A Deep Dive into AWS Reserved Instances</h3>

<p>One of our primary goals at Flux7 Labs is to help our clients reduce
their AWS costs. In fact, our product VyScale is based entirely on cost
optimization using Spot instances. We inform our clients when it makes
economic sense for them to buy instance reservations because
reservations for periods of unexpected minimum usage can be beneficial.
Reserved instances function exactly like on-demand instances, except
that you pay an upfront fee to gain cheaper hourly rates.</p>

<h3>Reserved Instance Pricing</h3>

<p>There are several levels of reservations. Higher ones allow you to pay
more up front in order to achieve a lower hourly cost. The table below
shows the rates for various types of reserved and on-demand instances
for m1.large instances.</p>

<hr />

<pre><code>           Upfront   Hourly in cents
</code></pre>

<p>  On-demand    0         24
  Light Util   243       13.6
  Med Util     554       8.4
  Heavy Util   676       5.6</p>

<hr />

<p>At some levels of utilization it makes sense to purchase reservations,
rather than to rely solely upon on-demand instances. By factoring in
upfront costs, we can determine which levels warrant purchasing
reservations. What’s surprising is that those levels are fairly low,
especially in the case of light reservations. Even at 30% utilization,
light-reservation costs start to break even with those of on-demand
instances. The following graph shows equivalent hourly costs for
reservations at various utilization levels</p>

<p><a href="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-1.png"><img src="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-1.png" alt="Hourl rates of reserved
instances" /></a></p>

<p>To better understand these numbers in terms of total cost, as opposed to
incremental cost, the figure below shows total annual expenditures at
various levels. For a 100% utilization of an instance, one can reduce
costs to almost half of Amazon’s standard pricing for reserved
instances, and that’s without any of the bulk discounts made available
to high-volume AWS customers. At lower levels, reservations cost almost
twice as much as those at higher levels. However, keep in mind that, as
a fraction of overall cost, the amount is still not very high. So, in
cases where growth is expected, it can make sense to purchase
reservations early.</p>

<p><a href="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-2.png"><img src="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-2.png" alt="Annual rates of reserved
instances" /></a></p>

<h3>Do You Have A Reservation?</h3>

<p>Another thing to know about Amazon’s policy is that you receive a
guaranteed instance when you buy a reservation, whereas there is no such
guarantee for on-demand instances. When trying to acquire an on-demand
instance, AWS may return an error message stating that capacity is not
available for that instance type. On the other hand, once you purchase a
reservation Amazon guarantees that the instance will be made available
to you at the moment you request it. If you’re using an autoscaling
solution it can make sense to make light utilization reservations to
handle your excess capacity, even if it costs more to guarantee uptime
to your customers. With Amazon’s guarantee it’s no wonder that Netflix
runs almost exclusively on reservations. As a matter of policy,
Netflix’s use of on-demand instances indicates that more reservations
need to be purchased.</p>

<p>One thing to note is that Amazon always uses reservations first, so you
can’t keep unused light reservations as backups while using on-demand
instances for capacity.</p>

<h3>How Amazon Handles Unused Reservations</h3>

<p>Spot instances are one of the best uses of unutilized reserved capacity
with AWS. They come with no guarantee of availability, and can be taken
away from you at Amazon’s discretion at any time in order to fulfill
other customers’ needs. Spot prices hover around 15% of the on-demand
price, which allows Amazon to make a decent return on unused
reservations and while offering reservations at a relatively low price.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>The most common reason to use reservations is price, but there are also
other considerations. The final decision should be based on capacity
analysis from a business perspective.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
