<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: AWS | Balaji Vajjala's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/categories/aws/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-17T12:32:02-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Balaji Vajjala]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Deep Dive into AWS Reserved Instances]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/a-deep-dive-into-aws-reserved-instances/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T09:35:27-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/a-deep-dive-into-aws-reserved-instances</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3>A Deep Dive into AWS Reserved Instances</h3>

<p>One of our primary goals at Flux7 Labs is to help our clients reduce
their AWS costs. In fact, our product VyScale is based entirely on cost
optimization using Spot instances. We inform our clients when it makes
economic sense for them to buy instance reservations because
reservations for periods of unexpected minimum usage can be beneficial.
Reserved instances function exactly like on-demand instances, except
that you pay an upfront fee to gain cheaper hourly rates.</p>

<h3>Reserved Instance Pricing</h3>

<p>There are several levels of reservations. Higher ones allow you to pay
more up front in order to achieve a lower hourly cost. The table below
shows the rates for various types of reserved and on-demand instances
for m1.large instances.</p>

<hr />

<pre><code>           Upfront   Hourly in cents
</code></pre>

<p>  On-demand    0         24
  Light Util   243       13.6
  Med Util     554       8.4
  Heavy Util   676       5.6</p>

<hr />

<p>At some levels of utilization it makes sense to purchase reservations,
rather than to rely solely upon on-demand instances. By factoring in
upfront costs, we can determine which levels warrant purchasing
reservations. What’s surprising is that those levels are fairly low,
especially in the case of light reservations. Even at 30% utilization,
light-reservation costs start to break even with those of on-demand
instances. The following graph shows equivalent hourly costs for
reservations at various utilization levels</p>

<p><a href="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-1.png"><img src="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-1.png" alt="Hourl rates of reserved
instances" /></a></p>

<p>To better understand these numbers in terms of total cost, as opposed to
incremental cost, the figure below shows total annual expenditures at
various levels. For a 100% utilization of an instance, one can reduce
costs to almost half of Amazon’s standard pricing for reserved
instances, and that’s without any of the bulk discounts made available
to high-volume AWS customers. At lower levels, reservations cost almost
twice as much as those at higher levels. However, keep in mind that, as
a fraction of overall cost, the amount is still not very high. So, in
cases where growth is expected, it can make sense to purchase
reservations early.</p>

<p><a href="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-2.png"><img src="../../../wp-content/uploads/AWS-reserved-instances-2.png" alt="Annual rates of reserved
instances" /></a></p>

<h3>Do You Have A Reservation?</h3>

<p>Another thing to know about Amazon’s policy is that you receive a
guaranteed instance when you buy a reservation, whereas there is no such
guarantee for on-demand instances. When trying to acquire an on-demand
instance, AWS may return an error message stating that capacity is not
available for that instance type. On the other hand, once you purchase a
reservation Amazon guarantees that the instance will be made available
to you at the moment you request it. If you’re using an autoscaling
solution it can make sense to make light utilization reservations to
handle your excess capacity, even if it costs more to guarantee uptime
to your customers. With Amazon’s guarantee it’s no wonder that Netflix
runs almost exclusively on reservations. As a matter of policy,
Netflix’s use of on-demand instances indicates that more reservations
need to be purchased.</p>

<p>One thing to note is that Amazon always uses reservations first, so you
can’t keep unused light reservations as backups while using on-demand
instances for capacity.</p>

<h3>How Amazon Handles Unused Reservations</h3>

<p>Spot instances are one of the best uses of unutilized reserved capacity
with AWS. They come with no guarantee of availability, and can be taken
away from you at Amazon’s discretion at any time in order to fulfill
other customers’ needs. Spot prices hover around 15% of the on-demand
price, which allows Amazon to make a decent return on unused
reservations and while offering reservations at a relatively low price.</p>

<h3>Conclusion</h3>

<p>The most common reason to use reservations is price, but there are also
other considerations. The final decision should be based on capacity
analysis from a business perspective.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[6 reasons why large enterprises should move to Amazon Web Services]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/6-reasons-why-large-enterprises-should-move-to-amazon-web-services/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-25T09:13:48-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2014/03/25/6-reasons-why-large-enterprises-should-move-to-amazon-web-services</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>6 reasons why large enterprises should move to Amazon Web Services</h2>

<h3>6 reasons why large enterprises should move to Amazon Web Services</h3>

<p>Amazon has changed the face of the world of startups with its cloud services. Now it’s possible for two men in a garage to set up large
computer clusters for zero capital cost.</p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/share?text=Amazon+has+its+sights+set+on+enterprise,+which+they+will+conquer+slowly+but+surely.+&amp;via=OurLabs&amp;related=Flux7Labs&amp;url=http://wp.me/p4sEOD-o6">Amazon has its sights set on enterprise, which they will conquer slowly
but
surely.</a></p>

<p>At Our Labs, one of our specialties is cloud migration for enterprise
clients, and we’ve received considerable feedback about both their
concerns and delights. In this post I’ll explain why I strongly believe
large enterprises should consider moving to the cloud.</p>

<h2><strong>Agility and Responsiveness</strong> </h2>

<p>Let’s face it, if a startup is a speedboat, then a large enterprise is
the Titanic. While startups can pivot any time there’s danger and large
enterprises turn more slowly, there are icebergs that can sink either.
Disasters happen to everyone, but a large enterprise has significantly
more skin in the game, and the old model of waiting a month before
buying a new rack just doesn’t cut it anymore. By shifting to the cloud,
large enterprises can bring up new servers in minutes, which means
shorter downtimes, rapid experimentation, more innovation, increased
global reach, improved demand-surge handling and more successful
short-lived-but-resource-intensive projects.</p>

<h2><strong>Innovation</strong> </h2>

<p>Business is a cutthroat world in which we must always strive to
out-innovate our competitors. This article is about the cloud in
general, but I want to explain why it’s also Amazon focused. Amazon has
been blazing the cloud-computing trail longer than anyone, which is
reflected by its 80% market share, and is clearly ahead of its
competitors. For example, check out Gartner’s analysis of different
cloud providers in the chart below and you’ll see Amazon in a corner of
their own. In fact, Amazon so dominated the competition that Gartner had
to artificially lower the scale. Amazon is innovating at such a rapid
pace in providing new services and broadening its customer base that
competitors are struggling to keep pace.</p>

<p>The effect of this innovation is obvious to developers. Do you want to
provide Active Directory integration with Amazon? You can do that. Do
you want to save on data costs by using the Bittorrent protocol for
content distribution? You can do that. Do you want to put heavy compute
behind your mobile games? You can do that. Do you want to ramp up your
clients quickly with remote workstations? You can do that, too. With
Amazon Web Services you can do all of that and more. I’m a
certified<a href="file:///C:/Users/Vishnu/Documents/Our/SMM/Blog/WhyEnterprisemustAmazon_(REVISED_CLEAN">[1]</a>.docx#_msocom_1) 
AWS instructor, yet I learn something new about AWS every day as Amazon
constantly releases new features. The advantage of moving your business
to the cloud is that you can let your developers focus on your company’s
area of expertise while leaving the boilerplate to Amazon.</p>

<p>\</p>

<p> <img src="https://lh3.googleusercontent.com/GmdBmLBmcGW9TIBqUCVkf403uIIf9arZ6-brIjBOt8tus6n_7YaKdOW3kcQqSIUbKnQd9vthqX1nyHHGouT8xbmDF3-xkpXUbJV0UJLpguSzg7EKB6QuaqR92uw_og" alt="" /></p>

<h2><strong>A Data Center That Hosts A Top Website</strong> </h2>

<p>One thing we mustn’t forget is what the AWS cloud really is—a product of
years of innovation by one of the largest e-commerce websites in the
world. Its data centers are distributed globally in numerous parts of
the world, with multiple, independently-operating data centers in each
region that provide different failure domains while being close enough
together to provide cheap communication. And that’s just the compute
side of the equation. Amazon also shares its global content distribution
network, its DNS servers. it compiles traffic data from across the globe
to find the best route for your network traffic. There are only a
handful of companies today with that kind of global reach, and they,
too, are developing cloud capabilities. But unless you’re in that elite
club, you won’t be able to create a data center that can compete with
AWS. So by using a cloud solution, rather than an in-house solution,
you’ll clearly benefit in terms of better performance, better fault
tolerance, and better disaster recovery.</p>

<h2><strong>Security</strong> </h2>

<p>Security is the biggest concern about cloud computing for most
enterprises, but Amazon holds many of the most important certifications,
including PCI, HIPAA, Sarbanes-Oxley, and ISO. Since it has so much at
stake, it maintains separation of logical and physical access to data in
order to limit the impact of disgruntled employees. While I certainly
understand someone hesitating to entrust one’s most valuable information
with a third party, it’s certainly debatable whether on-premise storage
is more secure than cloud storage.</p>

<h2><strong>In-house Expertise Not Required</strong> </h2>

<p>Anyone that’s had to hire people knows that good employees are worth
their weight in platinum. Moving to the cloud allows you to offload much
of your data-center maintenance onto Amazon. Let it do what it’s best at
while you focus on what you’re best at.</p>

<p>As we know, you often have to pay dearly to hire someone outside of your
area of expertise. For example, say you’re a director of IT at a company
like Schlumberger. Your company is great at what it does and has strong
brand value in its area of expertise. Do you think you can possibly
poach someone like <a href="http://mvdirona.com/jrh/work/">James Hamilton</a> for
your company? No, you can’t. With core expertise in data centers, Amazon
will likely offer a more intriguing challenge and a deeper sense of
mission to the kind of people you’ll want to hire for your team. And we
all know that employee engagement is not about the money, but rather
about being involved in a greater mission.</p>

<h2><strong>Lower Costs</strong> </h2>

<p>While I’m convinced that moving to the cloud will lower your costs, I
acknowledge that getting there requires a lot of expertise and hard
work. Additionally you may very easily find yourself comparing apples
and oranges. Yet cloud solutions are cheaper than on-premise solutions
when played right. First, when you pay for a machine on AWS you’re also
paying for Amazon’s years of expertise in setting up resilient data
centers, something that’s not true for in-house departments lacking core
IT expertise. Second, there’s great potential for saving money by
scaling to your variable demand needs instead of designing for max
capacity. That’s why Netflix, even though it comprises one-third of the
Internet in terms of data volume, has gone “all in” on AWS, or they’d
have to provision enough machines to handle 9PM Friday traffic.
Alternatively you can have an expected area of needing high demand, as
say for a chip company close to tapeout, a movie studio needing to
render for a year
(<a href="http://gigaom.com/2014/03/02/the-oscars-how-american-hustles-fx-team-made-2013-boston-look-like-1980s-new-york/">http://gigaom.com/2014/03/02/the-oscars-how-american-hustles-fx-team-made-2013-boston-look-like-1980s-new-york/</a>),
or a game company handling launch day demand
(<a href="http://www.respawn.com/news/lets-talk-about-the-xbox-live-cloud/">http://www.respawn.com/news/lets-talk-about-the-xbox-live-cloud/</a>).</p>

<h2><strong>Conclusion</strong> </h2>

<p>If you’re a large enterprise and on the fence about whether or not to
move to the cloud, we highly recommend trying it out. Try it on a
contained project, rather than one that’s on a critical path, something
that fits well within the cloud’s capabilities. After implementation, do
a post-mortem and analyze the results in terms of cost and
time-to-market. What is the expectation as you build in-house
expertise<strong>.</strong> The results may well surprise you.</p>

<h2><strong>Let’s Talk</strong> </h2>

<p>Our Research Labs has helped Fortune 100 and Fortune 500 companies move
successfully to AWS. We’d love to hear any questions, comments or
concerns you may have, so feel free to contact us anytime during weekly
<a href="http://ohours.org/aatersuleman">office hours</a> to discuss your specific
needs or situation. We offer this service free of charge with no
obligation or strings attached.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
