<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Technology | Balaji Vajjala's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-21T12:49:28-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Balaji Vajjala]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Programming]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2011/06/20/learning-programming/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-20T13:46:54-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2011/06/20/learning-programming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was tutoring someone in web app development recently, and the monumental task in front of him really hit me. <strong>He was trying to learn and use nine new languages at the same time</strong>.</p>

<p>In our case it was:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>Ruby</p></li>
<li><p>Rails</p></li>
<li><p>MySQL</p></li>
<li><p>Bash (command line usage)</p></li>
<li><p>HTML</p></li>
<li><p>CSS</p></li>
<li><p>Javascript</p></li>
<li><p>JQuery</p></li>
<li><p>Git</p></li>
<li><p>(Capistrano, Yaml, nginx, ??)</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Even though some of these aren&rsquo;t true languages in the traditional sense, they appear this way to newcomers since they are each a new syntax to learn.</p>

<p>If you slowly built up these skills over 15 years, they are clearly separate concepts in your mind. But for a newcomer trying to use them, it&rsquo;s not even clear which one is which.</p>

<p>Is that a Ruby method or a Rails method?</p>

<p>Is &ldquo;script/server&rdquo; a shell command or is &ldquo;ls&rdquo; part of rails?</p>

<p>Is this file html, js, or css? (actually a mix of all three)</p>

<p>He made a comment along the lines of &ldquo;wouldn&rsquo;t it be great if you could build an entire web app in one language&rdquo;, and I started thinking about it.</p>

<p>GWT (Google Website Toolkit), ActiveRecord, CoffeeScript, and Heroku are all steps in this direction. You could classify them generally as trying to &ldquo;eliminate a language in the stack&rdquo; or allowing you to do a piece of the stack in a language you already know.</p>

<p>Obviously there is a trade off here between power and simplicity, but I&rsquo;m wondering &ndash; would it be possible or desirable to get an entire web app down to just one language? If not that how few could you use?</p>

<p>Btw, I think there are benefits to seasoned developers here as well. I remember Lars Rasmussen (creator of Google Maps and Wave) mentioned something to this effect at Google IO in 2009, that GWT allowed him to spend his mental CPU cycles at a higher level and be more creative (not having to worry about cross browser css or js). So the benefits of higher abstraction may not only be for newcomers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
