<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: information | Balaji Vajjala's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/categories/information/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-16T12:49:58-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Balaji Vajjala]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Tech on my radar]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2012/04/19/tech-on-my-radar/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-19T23:19:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2012/04/19/tech-on-my-radar</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here are just some interesting gems and other software that have caught my attention recently:</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/robbyrussell/oh-my-zsh">oh-my-zsh</a> makes it easy to use zshell as a replacement for bash on OS X. It is very easy to install and comes with a whole bunch of useful plugins. I&rsquo;ve only really dived half into it but already feel like it&rsquo;s been making my console better. I personally love how it shows the Git branch I&rsquo;m working on at the moment.</li>
<li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bloom_filter">Bloom Filters</a> are a very cool way of doing a quick and space efficient lookup if an item exists in a set. It&rsquo;s used by databases and caches, and Google uses it for their Save Browsing service. There&rsquo;s some cool <a href="https://github.com/igrigorik/bloomfilter-rb">ruby gems</a> that make it easy to use them and I already have an idea where to deploy them next.</li>
<li><a href="http://zachholman.com/talk/how-github-uses-github-to-build-github">How Github uses Github</a> is pretty much how we use Github at EmberAds. The more we do it the more I see the benefits especially:

<ul>
<li>We work asynchronously</li>
<li>We use the hell out of Campfire</li>
<li>Master is always deployable</li>
<li>Pull Requests are our code reviews, requests for comments, and discussion boards.</li>
<li>Other apps have great features like prioritising stuff. But honestly, we have barely touched BaseCamp in weeks.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/EmberAds/cuuid">Fast UUID generation</a> is something we needed at EmberAds seeing as we use UUIDs everywhere and most of the Ruby gems were rather slow.    <a href="http://caius.name">Caius</a> cooked up a Ruby gem that uses a native C library which in our simple benchmarks spit out UUIDs about 6x faster.</li>
<li>On that note, <a href="https://github.com/EmberAds/acts_as_uuid">acts_as_uuid</a> is what we use to store UUIDs on our models in Postgres.</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/ondrejbartas/rake-progressbar">Rake progressbar</a> makes it easier for me to understand if I can go and make a brew or not when some of my rake tasks are running.</li>
<li>And finally, static site generators like <a href="http://nanoc.stoneship.org/">Nanoc</a>, <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a>, and <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> (used on this site) have been really catching my eye lately. Mainly because of the security and scaling implications. I&rsquo;ve been working on a blog post on this, mainly to inspire regular bloggers that you don&rsquo;t need a big server and a massive database to render a Wordpress site that will load slow as hell regardless.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A new blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2012/04/07/a-new-blog/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-07T15:17:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2012/04/07/a-new-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It has been a while since I last blogged, and to be fair I&rsquo;ve been kinda busy, but I also was frustrated with my old blog. It was bloated and heavy to load, all mainly due to Wordpress and Site5&rsquo;s shared hosting. Wordpress started as a nice blogging platform but lately it has been pissing me off (more on this), and I realised that running a whole PHP script for pages that barely ever change is stupid.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>So here is the new blog. The old one is still available <a href="http://blog.cristianobetta.com/">here</a> as a static HTML archive (hence why it loads so fast).</p>

<p>This new blog is built using <a href="http://octopress.org">Octopress</a>, which is a &ldquo;blog aware static site generator&rdquo;. Basically what it does is convert a whole folder of template files and blog posts written in <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">MarkDown</a> into a whole folder of HTML, CSS, and Javascript. I&rsquo;ve been using a few simple frameworks like <a href="http://nanoc.stoneship.org/">Nanoc</a> and <a href="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</a> for work and event management recently and I loved the speed. No database and no server side scripting results in super fast load times, combing that with the hosting on <a href="http://pages.github.com">Github</a> (see here to learn how to do this yourself) makes it even faster.</p>

<p>But let&rsquo;s quit talking about the technical details of my blog, or maybe not. I definitely want to share some more techie things here, highlight some of the code I personally write, workflows we use at <a href="http://emberads.com/">EmberAds</a>, and software I love using. Although it&rsquo;s fun to blog about anything at random, I rather make this blog a bit more topical (hence the cheesy title).</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
