<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Humor | Balaji Vajjala's Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/categories/humor/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-14T15:14:34-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Balaji Vajjala]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Embrace Big Data]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2013/01/15/embrace-big-data/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-15T07:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2013/01/15/embrace-big-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/posts/BigData.jpg"></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Math and Physics of Benderama]]></title>
    <link href="http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2011/06/27/math-and-physics-of-benderama/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-27T08:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bvajjala.github.io/blog/2011/06/27/math-and-physics-of-benderama</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The last episode of <a href="http://theinfosphere.org/Benderama">Futurama</a> has interesting formula involved. The entire plot is based on the Professor&rsquo;s latest invention &mdash; <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Banach&amp;#8211;Tarski_paradox">Banach-Tarski</a> Dupla-Shrinker &mdash; the machine that produces two copies of any object at a 60% scale. It was just a matter of time when Bender found a proper usage of this machine: to replicate himself. Then two small copies of Bender replicated themselves making four smaller copies, and so forth. At some point the Professor horrified the crew that if they don&rsquo;t stop this unlimited growth, the total mass of all Benders will eventually be so big that the entire Earth will be consumed during the process of replication. As a proof he demonstrated this formula of the mass of all generations of Bender</p>

<p><img class="center <a" src="href="http://pool.theinfosphere.org/images/thumb/0/04/Benderama_Maths.png/800px-Benderama_Maths.png">http://pool.theinfosphere.org/images/thumb/0/04/Benderama_Maths.png/800px-Benderama_Maths.png</a>"></p>

<p>This is a perfect toy for a science geek. The first obvious question it brings: is this formula mathematically correct? As it turns out, it is not. Considering the scale of 60%, the cubic dependency of volume on linear dimension, and the constant density of all copies, the formula should be the following</p>

<p>$$
M = \displaystyle\sum\limits<em>{n=0}^\infty 2<sup>n</sup>\left[\left(\frac{3}{5}\right)^{3n} M_0\right] = \displaystyle\sum\limits</em>{n=0}^\infty 2<sup>n</sup>\left[\left(\frac{27}{125}\right)<sup>n</sup> M_0\right] = \displaystyle\sum\limits_{n=0}^\infty\left(\frac{54}{125}\right)<sup>n</sup> M_0 = \frac{125}{71} M_0
$$</p>

<p>As you can see the total mass of infinite number of Benders actually converges to approximately 1.76 <em>M</em><sub>0</sub>. So from Math perspective there is nothing to worry about. But what if our assumption of constant density is invalid. Would it be a problem from Physics perspective? Let&rsquo;s see.</p>

<p>Knowing that every new copy has a size of 0.6 of the original it was made from, we have the following formula for the size of Bender in the <em>n</em><sup>th</sup> generation</p>

<p>$$
L_n = 0.6<sup>n</sup> L_0
$$</p>

<p>This exponential function becomes very small pretty soon. In the <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=0.6%5E154">154</a><sup>th</sup> generation it already reaches the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck_length">Planck length</a>, after which the further replication is physically impossible. If we calculate the total mass of 154 Bender&rsquo;s generations using the Professor&rsquo;s formula, we get <a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=H%28154%29">H(154)</a> &#215; <a href="http://www.peelified.com/Futurama-Forum-1/Topic-4095-0-Benders_Weight.html">238</a> kg &#8776; 1,337.56 kg, which is nothing comparing to the Earth mass.</p>

<p>So we have to admit that from both Math and Physics perspective the Professor was wrong, and there was no real threat to the Earth.</p>

<p>Although the Professor&rsquo;s formula doesn&rsquo;t describe the replication process adequately, it&rsquo;s still a beautiful piece of Math because it&rsquo;s a formula of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Harmonic_series_(mathematics)">harmonic series</a>. If you want to know why harmonic series is beautiful and which real processes it describes, read this nice <a href="http://plus.maths.org/content/perfect-harmony">article</a> of John H. Webb.</p>

<p>And don&rsquo;t miss the next <a href="http://theinfosphere.org/Ghost_in_the_Machines">episode</a> of Futurama this Thursday :&ndash;)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
